Carlos Montezuma papers, 1890-1922
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Carlos Montezuma papers, 1890-1922
AZ 287
Montezuma, Carlos, 1866-1923
This collection includes correspondence; manuscripts of lectures, articles, and reminiscences relating to his career and relationships with the federal government, reservations, and the Carlisle Indian School; and miscellaneous medical materials. Correspondents include officials of the Society of American Indians, American Indian Association, Progressive Indian Association, Richard H. Pratt, founder of Carlisle Indian School, as well as various relatives, friends, Native Americans, patients, and government officials.
1.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Carlos Montezuma, whose Indian name was Wassaja, was a Yavapai Indian from central Arizona. He was captured by Pima Indians and sold to a photographer. He was educated in Arizona and New York City. He graduated from the University of Illinois in 1884 and attended Chicago Medical College. Carlos Montezuma served as a reservation physician working for the Indian Services (BIA). While working on reservations he encouraged Native American children to go to school. He eventually became a Yavapai advocate for Native Americans and helped organize the Society of American Indians, a national lobbying group; and published Wassaja, a monthly indictment of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1899-1922
Series II: Lectures, Speeches and Articles, ca. 1907-1919
Series III: Miscellaneous Materials, ca. 1890-1913
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes correspondence; manuscripts of lectures, articles, and reminiscences relating to his career and relationships with the federal government, reservations, and the Carlisle Indian School; and miscellaneous medical materials. Correspondents include officials of the Society of American Indians, American Indian Association, Progressive Indian Association, Richard H. Pratt, founder of Carlisle Indian School, as well as various relatives, friends, Native Americans, patients, and government officials.
Related materials pertaining to Carlos Montezuma may be found in the following collections and repositories: Carlos Montezuma Papers, the Newberry Library, Chicago; Carlos Montezuma Collection, MSS-60. Arizona State University Libraries: Arizona Collection; and Carlos Montezuma papers on microfilm: inventory of collection at SW Studies Center, Fort Lewis College. University of Arizona Main Libraries also has a copy of The papers of Carlos Montezuma, M.D. [microform]: including the papers of Maria Keller Montezuma Moore and the papers of Joseph W. Latimer,(Micro- film 6709).
Access Terms
Montezuma, Carlos, 1866-1923 -- Archives
Pratt, Richard Henry, 1840-1924
Society of American Indians -- Correspondence
American Indian Association -- Correspondence
United States. Bureau of Indian Affairs
United States Indian School (Carlisle, Pa.)
Progressive Indian Association -- Correspondence
Indians of North America -- Government relations -- 1869-1934 -- Sources
Yavapai Indians -- Sources
Indians, Treatment of -- United States
Correspondence
Manuscripts
Speeches
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1899-1922
  - Correspondence: General Richard H. Pratt. 1907-1922 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence: General Richard H. Pratt (speeches and articles). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Montezuma to General Richard H. Pratt (drafts of letters). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Montezuma to various (drafts of letters). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: General. 1899-1916 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    Includes a letter from Alonso Stagg, University of Chicago, December 18, 1909.
  - Correspondence: F. A. McKenzie & Arthur C. Parker, Society of American Indians. 1904-1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Charles E. Dagenett, American Indian Association. 1911 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: August A. Breuninger, Progressive Indian Association. 1909-1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Cousins Richard Dickens, Charles Dickens, Mike Burns. 1904-1912 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II: Lectures, Speeches and Articles, ca. 1907-1919
  - Manuscripts: Lectures and Speeches
    - "The Primitive Indian." May, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Speech about Arizona. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Idealists on Indian Affairs." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Let My People Go." 1915 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Let There Be Light." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Mis-applied Philanthropy." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "The Reservation System." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Speech-For University." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Visit at Adamsville." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Missionaries Among the Indians." (Chicago). May 1913 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Columbus Conference Paper." (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "The Indian Problem." (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts: Carlisle Indian School and General Richard H. Pratt
    - "Reasons for Opposing Administration." (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Standing up for General Pratt's Dismissal, etc." (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Kill the Indian and Save the Man." (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Criticism of Indian Arrow." (School Weekly). (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Criticism on Sub Committee on Indian Affairs' Report to Stop Appropriation for Carlisle School." (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Averse to Converting Carlisle School into Indian Military School." (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Article on Carlisle School, Opposing its Removal." (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Mal-administration of the Carlisle School." Inter Ocean. April 20, ?? (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Carlisle's Indian Football Eleven." Philadelphia Public Ledger, p. 8. December 6, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscripts: Articles
    - "Abolish the Indian Bureau." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Blockades to Indian Civilization." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "The Development of the American Indian." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Electing a President." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Everybody Comes Into the World Blank." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Flash Lights on the Indian Question." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Get Right With the Indians - Bureau System." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Get the Indians Out." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Indian Faddists." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Indian Ideals." (Questioned if by Carlos Montezuma). (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "The Indian of Tomorrow." (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Missionary - not all." (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Indian Schools." (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Indian Superstition." (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Indian System Error." (2 versions). (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Indians and Indians." Published in Wassaja, vol. 1, no. 6. September 1916 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "The Indian's Art of Healing by Songs and Herbs." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Man's Inhumanity to Man." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Mistaken Policy." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "National Character." Tribune. May 1, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Plea for Arizona Indians." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Plea for the Indian - Starting with Self." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Plea on Behalf of the Pimas to Commissioner Sells." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Plea - with History of Self." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Review of Dr. Lydston's Book." (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Reminiscences of Self and Indian Character." (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Reservation Politics." (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Spiritualism of the Indians." (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Synopsis of Self." Review of Reviews. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Fragments, unidentified. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III: Miscellaneous Materials, ca. 1890-1913
  - Reminiscences. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous personal material. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Indian material. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes for and to the Secretary of the Interior. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fragments, mostly personal notes on self and Indians. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous medical material, including correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Medical reprints, speeches, etc. (Box 3, Folder 6)